<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Tangents on</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/</link><description>Recent content in Tangents on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>1 2 2023</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/1-2-2023/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/1-2-2023/</guid><description>don&amp;rsquo;t put ketchup on squirrels, paprika and teriyaki is fine; roasting squirrels is pretty fast, there isn&amp;rsquo;t much meat there kids got a skating rink in property, all the rain froze over, only melted 2 days ago; 2 inches of ice, 4 meters across Western Union still exists, for money; first job interned on a stage coach, literally road shotgun; back in the day, American idiomatic expressions, stagecoaches were very common as form of travel (like Cinderella) rider with reigns on left, person sitting on right (passenger seat on car) btw there were no cars, called riding shotgun because it was so dangerous, bandits rob people inside, ride holding a shotgun for protection (preferrably 12 gauge); people were paid in cash, try to rob it on paydays; hate people in historical places, they don&amp;rsquo;t break character (what&amp;rsquo;s the time?</description></item><item><title>1 4 2023</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/1-4-2023/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/1-4-2023/</guid><description>rubber door stops were removed, since states decided they were illegal; now states want people to keep doors open, so wooden door stops, giant pile of them; Frank, just drop one off out of the box, I know how to do it; can&amp;rsquo;t do it; laws being followed in this town?</description></item><item><title>1 9 2023</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/1-9-2023/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/1-9-2023/</guid><description>when a parent calls you a leach, it&amp;rsquo;s something perjorative Francis rants on Friday; saw him last week, asked if he was ok?</description></item><item><title>11 22 2022</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/11-22-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/11-22-2022/</guid><description> [[Hittinger]] rants [[Bitcoin]] [[Sports]] sarcasm, school abolished tests and sports [[Olympics]] random sports and teams Wallace interview pink unicorn sitting on desk STEM STEM was big a few years ago introduction in middle school Market child labor in sweat shops buying stuff made by kids America #1 in guns #1 in teen pregnancies</description></item><item><title>11 23 2022</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/11-23-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/11-23-2022/</guid><description>Pennsylvania, Bethlehem suspicious neighbourhood don&amp;rsquo;t go off campus Back to the Future Going down to the office Pleading the 5th 2022 seniors asking for lawyer [[Chris]] MLP unicorn meancing posture judging + concerned Driving, minivan, Metallica / Church Opera [[Howard Zinn]] Books back in the day, books had cover images when books still existed Utilitarian :: slavery, or administrative (Leela vs Ziccardi) [[Hittinger]] People in America don&amp;rsquo;t know how many branches of government there are who the Vice President is toupperware, eating in class tells students what the food is; unprompted (too much information) suggestion of roasted [[squirrels]] dipped in barbecue being on phone in class [[AP US Government]] art history student found [[Ziccardi]] in art room everyone just failed a test walked them to [[Hittinger]] room in us gov was REALLY hot opium den (?</description></item><item><title>11 28 2022</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/11-28-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/11-28-2022/</guid><description>Ran out of math classes Multivariable class invented for seniors of 2019 Senior needs math class to get to good school (they didn&amp;rsquo;t make it) Many years ago, some Ziccardi kids went to Stanford Can&amp;rsquo;t wear shoes at Berkely dress code Doing too much work on a Monday Plymouth rock (Massachussetts) metal iron fence; stuff vandalized over time there&amp;rsquo;s nothing there first Thanksgiving was a lie Pittsburg good city when America made stuff; it&amp;rsquo;s quite dull now before Richard Nixon, Henry Kissinger outsourcing took a hit on American manufacturing Latin reading about existentialism tiny class of 6 people (how was this allowed) Rich People indentured servants, butlers, maid First World Problems: kid complaining to another kid they can&amp;rsquo;t go home because house keeper was there &amp;ldquo;cramps their style&amp;rdquo;, talking loud in the library School Rooms Ap Government room is way too hot Auditorium is also very hot; should be colder History office is quite cold; someone complained, and now it's an oven Back in the day, everyone needed to be in History Office 2005, first renovation, created new offices, looks like a broom closet used to be across from Meritt; used to be in the trailers (for renovations) State found out the trailers were being used as classes, issues; trailers connected by dilapidated boardwalk, gotten rid of.</description></item><item><title>11 29 2022</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/11-29-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/11-29-2022/</guid><description>Inherited an extra class, dissing Art History class Flexing Chemistry in AP World Didn&amp;rsquo;t take physics, don&amp;rsquo;t believe in it Franciscis, emotional issues, but good person Standardized testing was made easier e.</description></item><item><title>12 1 2022</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-1-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-1-2022/</guid><description>Posner sang over the announcements in the morning singing over the PA is worse than waterboarding some administrators got angry someone random went into the office flutes are bad (flute in a rock band) kids are usually smaller than adults kids can usually read, not always told kids that squirrels were kosher, vienna schnitzel is vegan Americans are clueless people probably wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know Mozart is is he on TikTok nowadays?</description></item><item><title>12 2 2022</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-2-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-2-2022/</guid><description>doesn&amp;rsquo;t know what the reading next week is on :: qualified to go to college I saved 80 grand by having your kid not go to college newspapers Robert Massie (you know you've made it when you are on a NY Times obituary) Collective newspaper printings of famous historians in history office newspaper of Kennedy assasination, people that it was worth something, not much since everyone saved it; newspapers are not usually worth saving back in the day: there was not Internet, a lot more newspapers people were literate, enjoyed reading say no to children, like Nancy in the 80s, definitely wasn't a crack epidemic we no longer have newspapers on paper anymore, as it should be students should stick with wordsearches, spot the differences, where to put the sticker, crosswords too hard, like the other 7 year olds fake classroom for the state (yesterday) 2006, ranked 6th, 2000, ranked 1st (school ranking) why is it decreasing?</description></item><item><title>12 20 2022</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-20-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-20-2022/</guid><description>someone&amp;rsquo;s toupper ware is randomly in the room, doesn&amp;rsquo;t belong to anyone we know present both themes at once, it would be very good for students \s actually, the dates on the slide are wrong, doing research outside of school for indutrial revolution (the dates are a bit fuzzy) that&amp;rsquo;s just like Chinese, add s to make it plural (it&amp;rsquo;s funny because that&amp;rsquo;s not how it works) the guidance counselors could help you!</description></item><item><title>12 21 2022</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-21-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-21-2022/</guid><description>Pensyltucky is 17, 18, NJ is 07; As I write on all those college recommendations, don&amp;rsquo;t even need to mention &amp;ldquo;Road&amp;rdquo; at end of street name.</description></item><item><title>12 5 2022</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-5-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-5-2022/</guid><description>DBQ one year :: perspectives on the poor at a given point on history all the documents (?) occasionally give pure social history DBQs TBV Tangents throw the poor out of their homes, the peasants ruin the view smothering pillow, birth control at its finest US2 do they get rid of stuff in the book?</description></item><item><title>12 7 2022</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-7-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/tangents/12-7-2022/</guid><description>Previous history teacher gave simplified, abridged lessons, had to unteach all the kids Use Roman numerals rather than numbers for monarch&amp;rsquo;s names in AP FRQs.</description></item></channel></rss>