<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>notes on</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/tags/notes/</link><description>Recent content in notes on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://notes.tempera.dev/tags/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>1815-1914 Outline</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/1815-1914/notes/Outline/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/1815-1914/notes/Outline/</guid><description> 19th Century :: &amp;ldquo;The Age of Ideologies&amp;rdquo; Liberalism, Conservatism Nationalism, Socialism Industrial Revolutions 1st Industrial Revolution &amp;amp; 2nd Industrial Revolution Greater &amp;ldquo;polarization of society&amp;rdquo; Art Movements Romanticism, Realism, Impressionism &amp;ldquo;The Revolution of 1830&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;The Revolutions of 1848&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;The Age of Imperialism&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;New Science&amp;rdquo; &amp;amp; Philosophy Freud, Nietzsche, Social, Darw Unification of Italy &amp;amp; Germany 1914 = The First World War Class Notes [[europe/1815-1914/notes/Industrialization]] [[europe/1815-1914/notes/Politics]] TBV TBV 1 6 :: [[europe/1815-1914/notes/Industrialization in Great Britain]] TBV 1 11 :: [[europe/1815-1914/notes/Spread of Industrialization]]</description></item><item><title>Class Notes - England</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-England/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-England/</guid><description>England in the 17th Century English turns from [[cards/Absolutism]] to [[cards/Constitutionalism]] by end of 17th Century absolutist states -&amp;gt; soveriegnty resides with the monarch constitutionalist states -&amp;gt; sovereignty resides with the parliament No more [[Tudor|Tudor dynasty]] after 1603 ([[Elizabeth I]] dies) &amp;ldquo;Virgin Queen&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip; no progeny, but many suitors, (not a virgin) Distant cousins&amp;hellip; from Scotland, succeeded ruling line [[Stuart|The Stuart dynasty]] [[cards/James I]] (r.</description></item><item><title>France</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/1815-1914/notes/Politics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/1815-1914/notes/Politics/</guid><description>Important Ideologies Conservatism dominant ideology after the [[cards/Congress of Vienna]] from 1815-1848 1848 :: The Revolutions of 1848 Liberalism Nationalism Early Socialism [[cards/Louis XVIII]] r.</description></item><item><title>Industrialization</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/1815-1914/notes/Industrialization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/1815-1914/notes/Industrialization/</guid><description>Pre-Industrial Manufacturing &amp;ldquo;The cottage industry&amp;rdquo;, aka &amp;ldquo;the putting out system&amp;rdquo; visual of cart moving across, and cotton manufactured to cloth Families produced textiles in their rural homes.</description></item><item><title>Industrialization in Great Britain</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/1815-1914/notes/Industrialization-in-Great-Britain/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/1815-1914/notes/Industrialization-in-Great-Britain/</guid><description>TBV 1 6 Source: Spielvogel p 582-590
Economy government policies supported trade strong banking and paper notes system population growth -&amp;gt; more workers demand for textiles around the world -&amp;gt; market Cotton James Hargreave -&amp;gt; spinning jenny; yarn production Richard Arkwright -&amp;gt; water frame spinning machine Samuel Crompton -&amp;gt; mule (hybrid of previous 2) Edmund Cartwright -&amp;gt; power loom; cloth + yarn weaving organized labor near rivers {Source} :: analysis of Richard Arkwright&amp;rsquo;s success by Edward Baines math and English skills (sleep deprivation to train them) wife divorced him because not financially stable strong businessman Steam Engine deep coal mines replaced wood industry horses, then &amp;ldquo;atmospheric engines&amp;rdquo; to pump groundwater out of mines James Watt developed the superior rotary engine, more efficient coal usage, cotton imports, and textile production greatly increased actually decent undergarments pog Iron coke (coal derivative) smelt iron into pig iron through Cort Process Transportation roads -&amp;gt; canals -&amp;gt; railroads railways horsepower dependent, until Richard Trevithick&amp;rsquo;s steam-powered locomotive George Stephenson&amp;rsquo;s Rocket developed in Newcastle created jobs and investments into joint-stock companies reduce price of goods by speeding up transportation Factories workers shift from doing work to running machines; longer hours to maximize profit dismissals, fines, etc.</description></item><item><title>Notes - Absolutism</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-Absolutism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-Absolutism/</guid><description>Principles of Absolutism [[Absolutism]] monarchs: [[Peter the Great]], [[Charles I]], [[Louis XIV]] a political theory in this unit &amp;ldquo;A necessity as a result of the times&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; the 16th and 17th century were not peaceful, justified to prevent disorder emergence of strong, ambituous monarchs theoretical aspects greater control over [[subjects]], not [[citizens]] very centralized government age of &amp;ldquo;old conflict&amp;rdquo; between monarcho &amp;amp; nobles goal = curbing nobility&amp;rsquo;s power in practice religious orthodoxy efficient bureaucracy federal &amp;amp; regional &amp;ldquo;yes men&amp;rdquo; levy and collect taxes difference between asking and recieving collect and spend revenue on large standing armies and infrastructure global colonies to implement vvv [[Mercantilism]] Justification of Absolutism [[Thomas Hobbes]] 17th century political theorist ideas reflect the times, 17th century England tumultuous [[English Civil War]] a week of content (waow) Leviathan (1651) [[Absolutism]] was as absolute necessity very realistic view of human nature: competitive and uncooperative &amp;ldquo;Men are beasts&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Life is nasty, short, and brutish&amp;rdquo; [[Social Contract]] theory Strong monarch, avert anarchy Theorists used religion &amp;ldquo;Divine right&amp;rdquo; theorists &amp;ldquo;Embodiment of God on Earth&amp;rdquo;, therefore infallible [[Jean Bodin]] [[Jacques Bossuet]]</description></item><item><title>Notes - Agricultural Revolution</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-Agricultural-Revolution/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-Agricultural-Revolution/</guid><description>The 2nd Agricultural Revolution [[2nd Agricultural Revolution]] prerequisite for the Industrial Revolution impact on economy &amp;amp; demographics increased supply food, surplus precedent (first time in European History!</description></item><item><title>Notes - Austria</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-Austria/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-Austria/</guid><description>Maria Theresa [[Maria Theresa]] :: r. 1740-1780 did not have physical / developmental problems from inbreeding daughter of [[Charles VI]] (died in 1740) no male heirs, there was a daughter [[Pragmatic Sanction of 1713]] :: declares her as ruler collectively not accepted throughout Europe due to sexism neighbors (Prussia) &amp;ldquo;smelled blood&amp;rdquo; tried to take advantage of her ascendancy [[War of Austrian Succession]] :: 1740 - 1748 &amp;ldquo;The Silesian issue&amp;rdquo; (valuable land) never mentally recovered, husband died in 1765 16 children; 2 are important [[Joseph II]] :: &amp;ldquo;Enlightened&amp;rdquo; rule [[Marie Antoinette]] sister, [[Louis XVI]]&amp;rsquo;s wife; the &amp;ldquo;Austrian whore&amp;rdquo; Joseph II [[Joseph II]] :: reigned for mother 1765-1780, she was traumatized Promoted [[laissez-faire]] economics (renounced [[Mercantilism]]) Historically, Austria was Catholic [[Toleration Patent]] (1781) promoted religious freedom Seperation between government and church (secularism) reduced the role of the Jesuits in Austria Legit Music: no flutes Funded Mozart Career in Salzburg &amp;amp; Vienna &amp;ldquo;Court music&amp;rdquo; for aristocrats Education of commoners Legal reform (uniformity regardless of social class) Capital punishment reform [[Serfdom Patent]] :: 1781 emancipated serfs life got better, not perfect; treated humanely died from being overwhelmed after 10 years foreign policy &amp;ldquo;headaches&amp;rdquo; were his undoing Hungarians &amp;amp; the Ottomans exhausted him sadly, subsequent rulers reinstated status quo</description></item><item><title>Notes - Catherine the Great</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-Catherine-the-Great/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-Catherine-the-Great/</guid><description>Catherine the Great [[Catherine the Great]] :: r. 1762-1796 Not even Russian (the name Sophie became Ekaterina) Born in Stettin on the Baltic (Prussia) Arranged marriage to Peter III (also not Russian) not a very bright individual had him captured and secretly killed curious how her subjects lived &amp;hellip; (cared about common people) 1st tsar / tsarina to tour the countryside arranged by her senior advisor / lover, Grigory Potemkin &amp;ldquo;Potemkin villages&amp;rdquo; constructed to fool her :: poliitics and economics, now an idiom for deception, keeping up looks later in reign 3 pivotal events [[The Pugachev Rebellion]] :: peasant revolt, promptly crushed (doesn&amp;rsquo;t work) peasant claimed to be Peter III (real was dead) revolt to stop repression, popular amongst many peasants arrested and violently executed, movement crushed results feared peasant revolts afterwards favored &amp;amp; further empowered the boyars ironically serfdom became more repressive Beyond Russia in 1780s / 1790s ([[French Revolution]]) &amp;ldquo;ripple felt in Russian Empire&amp;rdquo; .</description></item><item><title>Notes - Enlightened Absolutism</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-Enlightened-Absolutism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-Enlightened-Absolutism/</guid><description>[[Enlightened Despotism]] rulers that voluntarily embraced ideals of Enlightenment in theory promoted reform based on Enlightenment ideals what were characteristics radical ideas for the 18th century &amp;ldquo;general will&amp;rdquo; ([[Jean-Racques Rousseau]]&amp;rsquo;s concept) freedom of speech education &amp;amp; literacy freedom of religion promoted the arts reform of criminal justice system equality before the law regardless of social class state funded STEM research &amp;ldquo;free trade&amp;rdquo; renounced [[Mercantilism]] secular outlook in government limit influence of organized religion why would rulers reform after having control utilitarian for administrative purposes efficiency in government, scientific political stability make life palatable for &amp;ldquo;unwashed masses&amp;rdquo; grant some reforms (keep the proles happy) don&amp;rsquo;t give them control over government don&amp;rsquo;t promote crazy ideas like liberal government avert revolution from below ruler could lose everything benevolent self-perception?</description></item><item><title>Notes - Enlightened Rulers</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-Enlightened-Rulers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-Enlightened-Rulers/</guid><description>Friedrich the Great Enlightened Behavior [[Friedrich der Große]] :: r.1740-1786 Prussian ruler (long existance) 1 of 2 dominant states within the [[Holy Roman Empire]] Austria was the other one (much bigger) viewed himself as The First Servant of the State Solidified Prussian status in Europe (becomes European power, despite being geographically small) Europe's most efficient army most efficient bureaucracy Doubled size of Prussia Economy expanded by means of State-funded domestic industries Most educated &amp;amp; cultured monarchs had [[Voltaire]] in his court Commissioned Sans Souci in Potsdam Rococo architecture Tolerance for Jews, Catholics, immigrants The Prussian Civil Code ratified Government positions based on skill, not ancestry More arable land cultivated New stable crops, vs rye + wheat; better for soil; turnips + potatos Life more palatable for masses Less than Enlightened Behavior [[Friedrich der Große]] Did not emancipate serfs, hands were tied by situation vast majority of the population would have suffered reprecussions from Junkers (Prussian Nobles) they were officers in his standing army Prolific flautist candle light flute solo oil painting Foreign relations doubled Prussia by aggression The Silesian issue [[War of Austrian Succession]]; 1740-1748 land &amp;amp; power; expense of [[Maria Theresa]] of Austria &amp;ldquo;Cooperated&amp;rdquo; with Austria and Russia over The Polish issue in the 18th C; Precarious location between the three countries, partitioned Poland vanishes until 1919 [[The Seven Years&amp;rsquo; War]] :: 1756-1763, annexed more land idolized by Hitler</description></item><item><title>Notes - French</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-French/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-French/</guid><description>Foundations of French Absolutism [[Henry IV]] is killed in 1610, regicide for promoting religious tolerance by Catholics [[Marie de Medici]] (wife) and [[Louis XIII]] (9 years old) Problem: 9 year old can&amp;rsquo;t do much [[Cardinal Richelieu]] advisor to [[Louis XIII]] until he came of age r.</description></item><item><title>Notes - Overview</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-Overview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/Notes-Overview/</guid><description>1648-1815 1815 Napoleonic War ends Congress of Vienna introduction of Eastern Europe, Prussia Austria &amp;amp; Russia! Europe becomes secular -&amp;gt; no more theology, HRE, or inbred Hapsburgs Economic changes -&amp;gt; [[Mercantilism]] vs Capitalism European statecraft [[cards/Absolutism]] (Bourbon) versus [[cards/Constitutionalism]] (Stuarts) Dutch Republicanism [[Enlightenment]] (18th Century) Enlightened Absolutism 2nd Agricultural Revolution The Dual Revolution (1789 - 1815) The French Revolution (May 5 of 1789) The 1st Industrial Revolution art + architecture social history, gender roles</description></item><item><title>Notes - The Dual Revolutions</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-The-Dual-Revolutions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-The-Dual-Revolutions/</guid><description>[[The French Revolution]] :: 1789-1815 [[The Industrial Revolution]] :: c. 1780s?-1914? 1st IR :: c. 1780s-1870s 2nd IR :: c.</description></item><item><title>Notes - The Restoration</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-The-Restoration/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-The-Restoration/</guid><description>The Restoration &amp;ldquo;Restoration&amp;rdquo; of monarchs across Europe Even though Napoleon defeated by 1815, can&amp;rsquo;t erase collective memories! The Congress of Vienna (1815) Diplomatic meeting; goal of restore conservatism by restoring monarchies &amp;ldquo;Erase the legacy of French Revolution &amp;amp; Napoleon&amp;rdquo; Dominated by conservative delegates from: Austria, Prussia, Russia &amp;amp; Great Britain Conservatism Strong (1815-1914) &amp;ldquo;shining star&amp;rdquo; (Austrian statesman) Klemens von Metternich epitome of conservatism accomplishments Louis XVIII (r 1815-1824) Restore Bourbon Dynasty France a soverign state&amp;hellip; But &amp;ldquo;puppet state&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Balance of power&amp;rdquo; system = Equillibrium pledged &amp;ldquo;intervention&amp;rdquo; if any nationalist revolts in the future intervention quickly applied after 1815 1820: Spain &amp;amp; Naples revolted against Hapsburgs &amp;amp; crushed 1821-1832: Greek independence supported by COV</description></item><item><title>Spread of Industrialization</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/1815-1914/notes/Spread-of-Industrialization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/1815-1914/notes/Spread-of-Industrialization/</guid><description>TBV 1 11 Source: Spielvogel p. 593-606
Industrialization Europe Order of industrial prowess :: England &amp;gt; France &amp;gt; Germany &amp;gt; Belgium Manufacturing (textiles) localized in Britain; more spread out in other countries Germany was pretty far behind, until they discovered coal deposits in Ruhr Valley, overtaking Britain after 1850 America Samuel Slater :: British imigrant first US textile factory Harpers Ferry :: exchangeable parts for muskets Steamboats and railroads logistical improvements Factories target whole family of workers, then when births dried up, Rich got richer, poor maintained status b/c held purchasing power {Source} :: Mark Twain, Life on the Mississippi; sense of excitement and innovation along the river, specific scene from his novel Social Impact Population Population drastically increased; birth rates fell, but so did death rates; eventually overpopulation became an issue {Source} :: John Mitchel, The Last Conquest of Ireland, Great Irish famine; people starved to death b/c potato rot etc Irish lived in impoverished conditions, dirt huts while farming potatoes Famine drastically reduced population, mass emigration to US Urbanization Urbanization generally grew slower in places other than Britain Living conditions in cities were pretty bad (slums), motif of unsanitary conditions, cramped spaces, nonexistant plumbing, spread of disease, China level fake food Food and Drugs Act 1875 James Kay-Shuttleworth :: the poor need to be policed by the rich Edwin Chadwick :: secretary of Poor Law Commission, Report on the Condition of the Labouring Population of Great Britain argued for reform, pushed for Public Health Act -&amp;gt; National Board of Health received support, due to fear of cholera Industrial Middle Class bourgeois no longer is effective descriptor; lawyers, teachers, physicians, and government officials; craftspeople and shopkeepers lower entrepreneurs quickly went bankrupt, factories quickly changed hands Joshua Fielden :: acquired factory after running family sheep farm and looms in farmhouse William Radcliffe :: agriculture and family business, then acquired factory &amp;gt;1000 workers Darbys, Lloyds :: iron manufacturers | Barclays, Lloyds :: bankers | Trumans, Perkins :: brewers | they were all Quakers Lambtons, Northumberland; Curwens, Cumberland; Norfolks, Yorkshire; Dudleys, Staffordshire | mining enterprises mostly family run businesses, large scale corporate was only ~1890 Factory Work Industrial transition happened slowly, not all at once (not majority immediately moved to city) artisans and craftspeople remained the largest group of workers in 1st half of 19th century</description></item><item><title>TBV 11 16</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/TBV-11-16/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/TBV-11-16/</guid><description>p.443-447
Limits [[Absolutism]] monarchs held strong control over their countries, controlling policies, wars, and religion local governing bodies still existed, as suspicious extensions of the king&amp;rsquo;s will some monarchs, like [[cards/Louis XIV]] used the aristocracy, while others were restricted by it Polish Monarchy [[Sigismunde III]] (1587-1631) Swedish ruler of Poland wanted to create an empire, but weakened and decentralized the state Sejm Polish diet, controlled largely by landowners king elects needed to share power with the Sejm, focused on local interests liberum veto :: single dissenting vote stopped meetings, reduced power even further disorganized collection of nobles, which was difficult to control Dutch Republic 17th C was the &amp;ldquo;golden age&amp;rdquo; of Dutch republic Netherland&amp;rsquo;s revolt formed the United Provinces, recognized by [[Treaty of Westphalia]] political tensions [[William of Orange]] and the House of Orange; wanted to develop centralized government The States General (representatives from every province); wanted decentralized republic augmented by divisions in Calvanists Church religious tolerance for Catholics, Protestants, and Jews war against France and England caused Dutch to give [[William III]] stadholderate acquired throne of England in 1688, but died with no direct heirs burdened economy, England shipping rivalry led to commercial decline Life in Amsterdam refugees bolstered number of inhabitants (~30k-&amp;gt;60k) Spanish Netherlands intellectuals + Jews attracted by tolerance merchants + workers attracted to prosperity rapid growth prompted &amp;ldquo;urban expansion plan&amp;rdquo; 500 -&amp;gt; 1800 acres of land canal construction, better transportation, and storage of goods on upper stories ships used for herring fishing, and carrying products fluyt :: large capacity ship, used to transport volume of products Dam Square :: unloading port for cargo main port of the Dutch East + West Indian trading companies city turned raw materials into finished products, produced: woolen cloth, refined sugar, tobacco, glass, beer, paper, books, jewelry gun manufacturing quite lucrative due to mass of European wars Amsterdam Stock Exchange financial center, investments -&amp;gt; prosperity speculation and bank industry massive wealth disparity lower class :: beggars and unskilled laborers -&amp;gt; dangerous sailing jobs craftspeople :: artisans and manual laborers many business woman, widows could take their husband&amp;rsquo;s places in guilds professional class :: lawyers, teachers, bureaucrats nobles :: owned land, built fancy houses top :: shipyard owners, merchants, manufacturers effectively controlled the city Calvanist lifestyle slowly moved to lavish one</description></item><item><title>TBV 11 4</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/TBV-11-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/TBV-11-4/</guid><description>Absolutism in Central, Eastern, and Northern Europe The German States [[Treaty of Westphalia|Peace of Westphalia]] :: ended the [[The Thirty Years&amp;rsquo; War]] Brandenburg-Prussia [[Hohenzollern]] dynasty :: rulers of Bradenburg [[Friedrick William the Great Elector]] [[Friedrick III]] Austria [[Hapsburg]] lost German empire, but created new one in southeast Europe weak ruler, only had control over northwest Hungary [[Leopold I]] received Spanish Netherlands, and some Italian city-states after helping HRE was never absolutist due to scattered nationalities Italy [[Charles V]] defeated French in 1530, took control of Italy.</description></item><item><title>TBV 12 1</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-1/</guid><description>Joseph Steele + Richard Addison :: Spectator magazine Eliza Haywood :: Female Spectator editor {Source} Edward Gibbon :: The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire (society can never be lost) schools reinforced social classes focused on classics, rather than practical (reformed later) Göttinghen, Hanoverian School :: physical sciences Edinburgh :: Newtonian sciences Cesare Beccaria :: On Crimes and Punishment (oppose death penalty, deterrent &amp;gt; violence) {Source} :: breaking wheel, torture and capital punishment Medicine Padua &amp;gt; Leiden &amp;gt; Vienna physicians (grad) &amp;gt; surgeon (clinical experience) &amp;gt; apothecaries midwives Celebrations :: Christmas, Easter, Carnival Carnival :: opposite of Lent, celebrate excess taverns :: gathering place of common people drinking :: tons of alcohol chapbooks :: popular stories, sold to lower class + literacy upper class suppressed education of poor (fear) dissolution of [[Jesuits]] Joseph II :: Austrian ruler Edict on Idle Institutions :: only charitable / educational monastic orders Toleration Patent :: allowed private worship of other Christianities Ashkenazic Jews :: central Europe Sephardic Jews :: Turkey !</description></item><item><title>TBV 12 13</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-13/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-13/</guid><description>Spielvogel p. 561-568.
Rebellion The Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen passed as official French legislation Olympe de Gouges, female playwright, femnist advocate, ignored by National Assembly {Source} :: Declaratin of the Rights of Woman and the Female Citizen it&amp;rsquo;s pretty much a carbon copy of earlier, but replace some parts with counter male-dominance Women&amp;rsquo;s March angry women go to Versaille with tools / weapons / cannons, demanding food [[Louis XIV]] forced to Paris, brought much flour heads of murdered guards paraded on pikes (waow) Changes Catholic Order lost power, bishops forced to swear allegiance to Civil Constitution (new) 54% took oath, created solid base for counter-reformation Citizens all have same civil rights active -&amp;gt; age 25, taxes 3 days unskilled labor, 4.</description></item><item><title>TBV 12 5</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/TBV-12-5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-3/TBV-12-5/</guid><description>p533-547
Children population drastically increased :: reduced death rate, infant mortality; more food, less plagues focus on family, marrying off; breast feeding undignified (nobles) [[Jean-Racques Rousseau|Rousseau]]&amp;rsquo;s Emile, more children surviving, upper class cared more about children (not lower) infanticide :: suffocated in blankets, economic pressures foundling institutions :: orphanage, pretty bad 50-90% mortality, children bleak hard working futures birth control :: late marriage age (25-27), high illegitemacy rate, coitus (waow) child future :: farm work, textiles, seamstresses Agriculture more cultivated land, more yield, healthier livestock, better climate new crops :: alfalfa, turnips, clover; Columbian Exchange [[Jethro Tull]] :: hoes loosened soil, improved farming smaller farms bought up by plantations; farmers -&amp;gt; wage workers Economy bank loans -&amp;gt; lending -&amp;gt; gold / silver backed notes country&amp;rsquo;s wealth vs ruler&amp;rsquo;s wealth speculation, French Co.</description></item><item><title>TBV 12 8</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-8/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-8/</guid><description> social structure of France divided into 3 Estates: clergy, noble, peasantry church :: not taxed, fairly divided nobility :: controlled industry, power at expense of crown; closed group bourgeoisie :: serfdom replaced with rights to land bread prices skyrockted, incited chaos aristocrats and borgeoisie elites felt restrained by L&amp;rsquo;Ancien Regime bad harvests -&amp;gt; food price rising philosophes&amp;rsquo; ideas spread amongst people government almost went bankrupt due to extravagant spending cahiers de doleances :: lists of grievances immediately divided over voting by head, or by estate National Assembly formed, Tennis Court Oath {Source} :: Newspaper account of storming of Bastille; governer beheaded and head paraded marked beginning of physical revolt [[Louis XVI]] tried to add more guards, realized no one was following his orders royal inaction led peasants uprisings to increase overall just alot of confusion (idea king supported revolt) {Source} :: Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen it&amp;rsquo;s literally just the American Constitution but poorly translated</description></item></channel></rss>