<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Unit 4 on</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/</link><description>Recent content in Unit 4 on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Unit-4-Overview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Unit-4-Overview/</guid><description>Europe in the 18th Century Effects of the Scientific Revolution, Enlightenment The 2nd Agricultural Revolution (p193-197; 250-252) Enlightened Despots (p217-218) The 1st Industrial Revolution (p281-291), 1780s?</description></item><item><title>Notes - Absolutism</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-Absolutism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-Absolutism/</guid><description>Principles of Absolutism [[Absolutism]] monarchs: [[Peter the Great]], [[Charles I]], [[Louis XIV]] a political theory in this unit &amp;ldquo;A necessity as a result of the times&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; the 16th and 17th century were not peaceful, justified to prevent disorder emergence of strong, ambituous monarchs theoretical aspects greater control over [[subjects]], not [[citizens]] very centralized government age of &amp;ldquo;old conflict&amp;rdquo; between monarcho &amp;amp; nobles goal = curbing nobility&amp;rsquo;s power in practice religious orthodoxy efficient bureaucracy federal &amp;amp; regional &amp;ldquo;yes men&amp;rdquo; levy and collect taxes difference between asking and recieving collect and spend revenue on large standing armies and infrastructure global colonies to implement vvv [[Mercantilism]] Justification of Absolutism [[Thomas Hobbes]] 17th century political theorist ideas reflect the times, 17th century England tumultuous [[English Civil War]] a week of content (waow) Leviathan (1651) [[Absolutism]] was as absolute necessity very realistic view of human nature: competitive and uncooperative &amp;ldquo;Men are beasts&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Life is nasty, short, and brutish&amp;rdquo; [[Social Contract]] theory Strong monarch, avert anarchy Theorists used religion &amp;ldquo;Divine right&amp;rdquo; theorists &amp;ldquo;Embodiment of God on Earth&amp;rdquo;, therefore infallible [[Jean Bodin]] [[Jacques Bossuet]]</description></item><item><title>Notes - Enlightened Absolutism</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-Enlightened-Absolutism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-Enlightened-Absolutism/</guid><description>[[Enlightened Despotism]] rulers that voluntarily embraced ideals of Enlightenment in theory promoted reform based on Enlightenment ideals what were characteristics radical ideas for the 18th century &amp;ldquo;general will&amp;rdquo; ([[Jean-Racques Rousseau]]&amp;rsquo;s concept) freedom of speech education &amp;amp; literacy freedom of religion promoted the arts reform of criminal justice system equality before the law regardless of social class state funded STEM research &amp;ldquo;free trade&amp;rdquo; renounced [[Mercantilism]] secular outlook in government limit influence of organized religion why would rulers reform after having control utilitarian for administrative purposes efficiency in government, scientific political stability make life palatable for &amp;ldquo;unwashed masses&amp;rdquo; grant some reforms (keep the proles happy) don&amp;rsquo;t give them control over government don&amp;rsquo;t promote crazy ideas like liberal government avert revolution from below ruler could lose everything benevolent self-perception?</description></item><item><title>Notes - The Dual Revolutions</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-The-Dual-Revolutions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-The-Dual-Revolutions/</guid><description>[[The French Revolution]] :: 1789-1815 [[The Industrial Revolution]] :: c. 1780s?-1914? 1st IR :: c. 1780s-1870s 2nd IR :: c.</description></item><item><title>Notes - The Restoration</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-The-Restoration/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/Notes-The-Restoration/</guid><description>The Restoration &amp;ldquo;Restoration&amp;rdquo; of monarchs across Europe Even though Napoleon defeated by 1815, can&amp;rsquo;t erase collective memories! The Congress of Vienna (1815) Diplomatic meeting; goal of restore conservatism by restoring monarchies &amp;ldquo;Erase the legacy of French Revolution &amp;amp; Napoleon&amp;rdquo; Dominated by conservative delegates from: Austria, Prussia, Russia &amp;amp; Great Britain Conservatism Strong (1815-1914) &amp;ldquo;shining star&amp;rdquo; (Austrian statesman) Klemens von Metternich epitome of conservatism accomplishments Louis XVIII (r 1815-1824) Restore Bourbon Dynasty France a soverign state&amp;hellip; But &amp;ldquo;puppet state&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Balance of power&amp;rdquo; system = Equillibrium pledged &amp;ldquo;intervention&amp;rdquo; if any nationalist revolts in the future intervention quickly applied after 1815 1820: Spain &amp;amp; Naples revolted against Hapsburgs &amp;amp; crushed 1821-1832: Greek independence supported by COV</description></item><item><title>TBV 12 1</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-1/</guid><description>Joseph Steele + Richard Addison :: Spectator magazine Eliza Haywood :: Female Spectator editor {Source} Edward Gibbon :: The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire (society can never be lost) schools reinforced social classes focused on classics, rather than practical (reformed later) Göttinghen, Hanoverian School :: physical sciences Edinburgh :: Newtonian sciences Cesare Beccaria :: On Crimes and Punishment (oppose death penalty, deterrent &amp;gt; violence) {Source} :: breaking wheel, torture and capital punishment Medicine Padua &amp;gt; Leiden &amp;gt; Vienna physicians (grad) &amp;gt; surgeon (clinical experience) &amp;gt; apothecaries midwives Celebrations :: Christmas, Easter, Carnival Carnival :: opposite of Lent, celebrate excess taverns :: gathering place of common people drinking :: tons of alcohol chapbooks :: popular stories, sold to lower class + literacy upper class suppressed education of poor (fear) dissolution of [[Jesuits]] Joseph II :: Austrian ruler Edict on Idle Institutions :: only charitable / educational monastic orders Toleration Patent :: allowed private worship of other Christianities Ashkenazic Jews :: central Europe Sephardic Jews :: Turkey !</description></item><item><title>TBV 12 13</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-13/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-13/</guid><description>Spielvogel p. 561-568.
Rebellion The Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen passed as official French legislation Olympe de Gouges, female playwright, femnist advocate, ignored by National Assembly {Source} :: Declaratin of the Rights of Woman and the Female Citizen it&amp;rsquo;s pretty much a carbon copy of earlier, but replace some parts with counter male-dominance Women&amp;rsquo;s March angry women go to Versaille with tools / weapons / cannons, demanding food [[Louis XIV]] forced to Paris, brought much flour heads of murdered guards paraded on pikes (waow) Changes Catholic Order lost power, bishops forced to swear allegiance to Civil Constitution (new) 54% took oath, created solid base for counter-reformation Citizens all have same civil rights active -&amp;gt; age 25, taxes 3 days unskilled labor, 4.</description></item><item><title>TBV 12 8</title><link>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-8/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.tempera.dev/europe/Unit-4/TBV-12-8/</guid><description> social structure of France divided into 3 Estates: clergy, noble, peasantry church :: not taxed, fairly divided nobility :: controlled industry, power at expense of crown; closed group bourgeoisie :: serfdom replaced with rights to land bread prices skyrockted, incited chaos aristocrats and borgeoisie elites felt restrained by L&amp;rsquo;Ancien Regime bad harvests -&amp;gt; food price rising philosophes&amp;rsquo; ideas spread amongst people government almost went bankrupt due to extravagant spending cahiers de doleances :: lists of grievances immediately divided over voting by head, or by estate National Assembly formed, Tennis Court Oath {Source} :: Newspaper account of storming of Bastille; governer beheaded and head paraded marked beginning of physical revolt [[Louis XVI]] tried to add more guards, realized no one was following his orders royal inaction led peasants uprisings to increase overall just alot of confusion (idea king supported revolt) {Source} :: Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen it&amp;rsquo;s literally just the American Constitution but poorly translated</description></item></channel></rss>